Klarna is in trouble.
The company that pioneered
the Buy Now Pay Later trend, which
has pushed so many into debt,
seemed to be on top of the world.
A $17 billion IPO, growing revenue,
millions of new active users.
Now it’s collapsing.
Their stock is down 60%.
Their profits are even worse.
But something even weirder is happening.
Klarna is evolving into something else.
Something much bigger than
just “buy now, pay later”.
Yet, investors aren’t impressed.
And now, Klarna is facing a major
lawsuit, for a potentially misleading IPO.
Klarna is finally getting what they deserve.
Our last video on Klarna ended
on a very important moment:
The IPO, which they had delayed,
because of how bad things were looking.
On the surface, things were looking pretty good!
They passed 100 million active users.
Plus, the longer customers use Klarna, the
more often they use it. From 2x a year when they
sign up, to as high as 18x a year after 6 years.
[Sebastian Siemiatkowski, CEO, Co-Founder]:
“The momentum is undeniable. We're outpacing
competitors, our merchant network is
scaling rapidly, and our next-gen products
are reshaping money management for millions.”
But, Klarna was caught in a pretty ironic spot.
Klarna is basically the face
of “buy now, pay later”.
A merchant will add Klarna to your
checkout, and pay them 3-6% as a commission.
They then offer the customer the option to buy now
and pay in multiple installments, pay in 30 days,
or financing options, as long as 36 months!
The most common was to pay something
in 4 installments though.
But, there’s one crucial detail.
Klarna fronts the payment for the merchant, and
takes on the debt of what the customer owes.
So, they still have to get
that money back from the buyer.
Though, this is how they make money. Failed
payments charge $7, their debt has particularly
high interest, as high as 35.9%! They were
even dragged into court for charging €1.20
just for a reminder email.
Klarna is essentially a debt
collection company… just with good branding.
But this business model, creates some problems.
Even when Klarna reports huge revenue,
huge growth, and 100 million users,
they still have the problem of that debt.
In 2025, customer credit losses increased
by 17%, totalling $136 million. This means more
customers are failing to pay back their debt.
When Klarna pays merchants upfront, they
typically do this with their own debt. But,
with fewer customers repaying their debt,
Klarna's debt is getting more expensive.
Debt financing expenses climbed to
$130 million in Q1 2025, up 15%.
That's not Klarna's debt, that's the
cost of their debt, like interest.
Ironic as it sounds, Klarna has
fallen into their own debt trap.
Buy now, with debt, and pay it back later.
$130 million cost of debt, for just one quarter,
which is slowly rising. It makes you
wonder how massive Klarna's actual debt is.
Buy now, pay later users
are also disproportionately
financially vulnerable compared to other debt.
A study this year found that 41% of customers
had been late on a payment, up from last year.
This is why, despite their EBITDA saying they made
$3 million in profit, on 700 million in revenue,
they actually lost $99 million.
In one quarter too!
Not only is this ethically questionable,
it also causes these problems for Klarna.
But that brings us back to potentially the most
important moment for Klarna: The IPO along with
CEO and co-founder: Sebastian Siemiatkowski.
They had delayed their IPO,
which they said was due to tariffs.
But, I think he knew the Buy now pay later
model wasn’t sustainable. At least, on its own.
With how Klarna’s outlook was, I don’t think
an IPO would have been hugely successful.
They needed a story for Wall Street to buy.
That’s why, Sebastian had
even bigger plans for Klarna.
He’s had plans for a huge
pivot, into something else.
So Klarna began moving ahead with their IPO.
And… it was a huge success?
In September 2025, Klarna went public on the NYSE.
Priced at $40,
above the guidance range of $35-$37.
Demand exceeded supply by roughly 25 times.
Shares opened at $52 and closed
first day at $45.82, up 15%.
At closing, Klarna was valued at $17.4
billion, raising $1.37 billion total.
To outsiders, this seemed like a total home run.
Like all the worries about Klarna were gone.
But, not exactly.
Look at this graph.
Their market cap is down more than 50%.
The price is even lower.
Something weird is happening.
And now, Klarna is facing a major
lawsuit because of this IPO.
Klarna have been rebranding into something bigger.
If we look at their IPO, they describe themselves
as “the global digital bank and flexible
payments provider” in the first line.
The second part, is what Klarna
actually does. Flexible payments.
So what’s with the “Global digital bank”?
Klarna is changing, and not everyone’s
happy about it.
Let’s go a bit deeper.
The same week Klarna filed for an IPO,
it partnered with the company OnePay.
That’s basically Walmart’s payment company,
and Klarna is now the retailer’s exclusive
“Buy now pay later” provider.
Prior to this, Walmart exclusively
used Affirm, who has now been dropped.
[Sebastian Siemiatkowski, CEO, Co-Founder]:
“Choosing Klarna as their exclusive installment
loans partner at Walmart in the US is a huge
vote of confidence as we pursue our goal of
being available everywhere for everything.”
But something about all this is… weird.
First, Klarna issued OnePay warrants to
acquire 15.3 million Klarna ordinary shares, over
five years, with an average price of $34 each.
That basically means Klarna essentially
paid Walmart in stock for the partnership
with a cheaper share price, which
means they really wanted this.
At least, it was a cheaper share price.
But that’s not all.
Repayment options are 3 to 36 months,
with interest rates reportedly
ranging from 10% to as high as 36%.
Those loans are long and with interest.
In 2024, Klarna said 99% of transactions on
its network were interest-free. But no longer.
Klarna has been slowly trying to
pivot into larger, regular banking.
Specifically, through what they call: "Fair
Financing", those longer-term installment loans
typically spanning 6 to 24 months.
Basically, more of the normal,
interest based loans.
And Walmart was just the beginning.
In 2025, they also launched a debit card,
“as it looks to diversify its business
beyond short-term credit products”
And when did they do all of this?
Right before their IPO, which they
re-filed in September, and rebranded
themselves first as a “global digital bank”.
Klarna is “like” a bank… but they still aren’t?
Klarna does have a full banking
license in the EU, but not in the US.
So, they aren’t, but they can offer FDIC-insured
deposits and withdrawals, aka like a normal bank.
How? They go through a partnership
with WebBank, a small financial
institution based in Salt Lake City, Utah.
[Sebastian Siemiatkowski, CEO, Co-Founder]: "We
are basically a neobank to a large
degree, but people associate us still
strongly with buy now, pay later."
They’re doing this, because getting
your own US bank charter is so slow.
But this partner bank model gives them
90% of the benefits, with none of the hassle.
It’s the “Banking-as-a-Service” route. WebBank
holds the actual charter, Klarna rents it.
But why do this?
After all, the US banking industry
is very competitive, with giants like
JPMorgan Chase & Co and Bank of America.
Well, this might be Klarna’s only choice.
First, Buy now pay later
loans have terrible margins.
The loans were short, small,
and usually have no interest.
But interest, in finance, is the real money maker.
Plus, we know the rate of late
payments was rising, which likely
hurt Klarna’s cost of debt, and profit.
And then there’s the second reason.
I don’t think nearly as many
people would’ve invested in Klarna,
if they didn’t have a plan like this.
Pivoting to a “digital bank”? That’s
something you can sell to Wall Street.
So, the question is, did it pay off?
We just passed 900,000 subscribers,
and I wanted to say thank you! Thank
you for watching our videos; we
put a ton of effort into them.
If you’re not subscribed, maybe
you can help us get to 1 million!
We know the IPO was a huge
success, but after that,
things turned sour pretty quick.
Even if Klarna isn’t “technically”
the real bank here, they still hold the
credit risk for this “fair financing”.
Instead of just short term
loans, it’s long term ones too!
Higher revenue, from interest, and
more customers… but also more risk.
A few weeks after the IPO, Klarna
released their Q3 financials.
Gross Merchandise Volume (GMV), $32.7 billion,
up 43% thanks to rising long-term loans.
Plus 4 million card signups.
Revenue was 900 million,
up from 706 million year over year.
But net income was a loss of 95 million,
down from a profit of 12 million year over year.
And, the more important number: TMD — Transaction
Margin Dollars. Aka, Klarna's profit
on transaction after the direct costs
of funding and servicing the loans.
This is basically the key to whether
Klarna’s core business is working.
This was 281 million,
down from the same quarter the previous year.
But Klarna was confident, so they projected
TMD would grow to $390-400M next quarter.
Then came Q4 2025, and Klarna outperformed
its guided projections in revenue, and GMV…
But not TMD, though they did come close.
$372 million.
[Sebastian Siemiatkowski, CEO, Co-Founder]: "This
quarter's transaction margin dollar result
did not land where we guided. We take that
seriously. The acceleration in lending growth
is the primary driver of that outcome.”
Klarna missed their own projections,
but for a really ironic reason.
Fair Financing grew faster than
Klarna's own forecast — and that
faster growth is what caused the miss.
Based on the nature of fair financing,
those long loans, they have a big upfront
cost, but that profit lags quite a ways.
In that quarter, there were 2.5 billion in new
loans, which had $80 million in upfront losses,
with only $40 million in upfront revenue.
This is what’s hurting Klarna right now,
more of this long-term debt than expected.
The actual income, from interest and such
on that 2.5 billion, Klarna won’t see for a
while, which is expected to be 180 million.
That is, if borrowers pay as Klarna expect
them to. Just because you own lots of debt,
with “potential” earnings,
doesn’t mean it’s guaranteed.
The stock by this point, was down
more than 75% from their IPO.
But, something unexpected just happened.
In Q1 of 2026, Klarna finally reported
positive income.
Of… $1 million.
On revenue of $1 billion.
TMD was $389 million, more than
last quarter, but not by much.
Same goes for GMV too.
Fair Financing and being a “bank” was the
story for the “next big step” for Klarna.
But, is it really translating into more profit?
Well, many don’t think so.
Even after a sliver of profit,
the price is still flat.
Maybe there’ll be more profit growth, but so far,
the growth prospects aren’t great.
And there are other problems too.
On Dec 22, 2025, a shareholder
class action was filed against
Klarna “claiming the company misled
investors during its September 2025
IPO by downplaying credit risks in its
buy now, pay later lending business.”
Just weeks after the IPO,
Klarna reported a staggering
102% year-over-year increase in its
provision for credit losses, causing
shares to plunge well below the $40 IPO price.
[Reed Kathrein, Hagens Berman partner]: "When
a company's credit loss provisions double
almost immediately after going public,
it raises serious questions about whether
the IPO documents were truly transparent”
Klarna in response, said that “We
believe the allegations lack merit”.
This lawsuit is ongoing, but it’s pretty
clear many aren’t happy with Klarna’s choices.
And given how the stock essentially
nosedived after the IPO, it’s understandable.
One of the weirdest parts about Klarna though, is
actually their obsession with AI replacing humans.
But these aren't working as well as many thought.
AI customer service and AI layoffs are actually
backfiring for a lot of companies, and many,
including Klarna, are starting to regret it.
Click here to learn the rest of the story.